Guide to the Kay Leigh Hagan Papers, 1955-2012 RL.00490
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kay Leigh Hagan papers
1955-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hagan, Kay Leigh
RL.00490
955
27 Linear Feet 21,375 items
Kay Leigh Hagan is a writer, teacher, and feminist. Much of her early career focused on raising women's consciousness by teaching how to recognize various forms of internalized oppression in private classes she called "Feminars". In addition to her writing and teaching, this collection documents Hagan's many public speaking appearances and workshops, including those at womyn's music festivals (1988-2000). Her published works include Fugitive Information: Essays from a Feminist Hothead (1993), Internal Affairs: A Journal Keeping Workbook for Self-Intimacy (1990), Prayers to the Moon: Exercises in Self-Reflection (1991), and Vow: The Way of the Milagro (2003) with photographer Richard Downing. She was also the editor of Women Respond to the Men's Movement: A Feminist Collection (1992), and co-author of A Peculiar Alchemy (2007), a centennial history of the School for Advanced Research, with Nancy Owen Lewis. She has been active in Atlanta, Georgia, where she was affiliated with Forrest Avenue Consortium (later Nexus Contemporary Art Center) and Charis Books & More; and Santa Fe, New Mexico, where she worked with Los Alamos National Laboratory and the School for Advanced Research, among other organizations.
Access Restrictions
Hagan's journals and correspondence are closed to research until 2043 or the death of the donor, whichever is later.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Kay Leigh Hagan Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Biographical Note
Kay Leigh Hagan was born in Winston Salem, North Carolina, in 1949. She grew up there until attending the University of Georgia in Athens, where she earned her B. A. in journalism in 1971 and met Jack Leigh, a photographer from Savannah. They were married from 1972-75. In Atlanta, Georgia, she became active in the alternative arts movement in 1977 as co-director of Forrest Avenue Consortium, and the women's movement in 1980 as a partner at Charis Books & More. She taught private classes and workshops across the country for women on keeping journals and identifying internalized oppression, then wrote and published several books. She was active in the independent press and feminist bookstore movements, self-publishing two books later reissued by mainstream publisher HarperCollins. She lived in Santa Fe, New Mexico, from 1992-2013, then moved to Washington, DC, and married Pamela D. Coleman.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of art objects, artists' books, video recordings, audio recordings, research files, drafts of published works, writings, journals and correspondence, materials documenting Hagan's political activism and private teaching, materials documenting her work with the School for Advanced Research, and graphic materials.
Collection was acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Separated Material
Some of Hagan's published works have been removed for separate cataloging.
Related Archival Materials note
Other materials related to Charis Books and More in Atlanta can be found in the Charis Books and More and Charis Circle Records
Other materials related to Julia Penelope can be found in the Julia Penelope Papers.
Audiocassettes; Feminists -- United States -- Santa Fe (N.M.); VHS; Feminists -- United States -- Atlanta (Ga.); Photographs; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Artists' books by women; DVDs; Penelope, Julia, 1941-; School for Advanced Research (Santa Fe, N.M.); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Charis Books and More; Finnel, Linda, 1948-1999; Geiser, Janie; Hagan, Kay Leigh -- Fugitive Information; Hagan, Kay Leigh; Nexus Press
- Art Objects and A/V Material, 1978-2005, 326944; 2 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Relay Relay Shun Ships. Inscribed by Janie Geiser, ca. 1984: Box diorama, comment on the hazards of conventional couple relationships; i.e., to avoid the treacherous waters of mind-deadening cruise control of coupling, one should relay relay (communicate) and shun ships (avoid the cruise liner mentality). The two people on the tightrope are being mindful of this observation., 326965 (Box 1)
  - Rune Box by Linda Finnell. Contents: Solstice Ornament by Janie Geiser with photo of Hagan incorporated in design, and some of her hair inside the envelope; deerskin pouch with painted bone by Deborah Brink; Roller Skate Fairy quilt fragment (hand with wristwatch) by Linda Finnell, and Red Diorama of Woman Spinning by Janie Geiser., 326964 (Box 1)
  - Black Cigar Box, interior painting-collage by Janie Geiser. Contents: Lace heart and box by Linda Finnell, Oath of the Bitches from Hell by Deborah Brink (inspired by Fugitive Information essay "Bitches from Hell", Blue Dog by Janie Geiser, small warrior woman figuring, beaded bracelet., 326963 (Box 1)
  - Basket filled with political buttons, 326962 (Box 1)
  - Artist book by Janie Geiser, 1978, 326961 (Box 1)
  - Plastic box with Michigan Womyn's Music Festival worker patches and lapel pin from 5th International Feminist Book Fair, 326960 (Box 1)
  - Half and whole egg ceramic hanging ritual objects by Suzanne Bellamy, 326959 (Box 1)
  - Painted antler bone by Deborah Brink, 326958 (Box 1)
  - Various photographs, 326957 (Box 2)
  - Karen Klue images, 326956 (Box 2)
  - Hothead Express photo album bound by Linda Finnell, 326955 (Box 2)
  - Feminist Hullabaloo by Sonia Johnson, Santa Fe, ca. 2005, 326954 (Box 2)
  - Women Respond to the Men's Movement, Hagan appearance on Phil Donahue Show, ca. 1993 (video), 326953 (Box 2)
  - An Inner Voice, Linda Finnell (video), 326952 (Box 2)
  - Ask Kay, by C. June Bryant, 1986 (video), 326951 (Box 2)
  - Creating a Personal Culture, with Hagan, by Joan E. Biren, Rhythm Fest, 1990 (video), 326950 (Box 2)
  - Hotchkiss Lecture, Hagan and Michael Kimmell, 1994 (DVD), 326949 (Box 2)
  - Illinois Wesleyan College, Hagan and Michael Kimmell (DVD), 326948 (Box 2)
  - Journal Workshop with Hagan, Dallas TX, early 1980s (video), 326947 (Box 2)
  - Keynote address by Hagan Celebration '95, New Orleans, Lesbian and Gay Conference (DVD), 326946 (Box 2)
  - "A Woman's Place", TV interview with Hagan, Atlanta, 326945 (Box 2)
- Journals and Correspondence, 1970-2012, 326941; 5 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access note
  RESTRICTED: All Hagan's journals and correspondence are closed to research.
  - Journals, 326943 (Box 3-4)
  - Correspondence, 326942 (Box 6-7,9)
- Published Works and Writings, 1969-2012, 326924; 6 boxes
  - Publication materials, including manuscript drafts and correspondence, and research files for the books Internal Affairs (including letterpress poems), Prayers to the Moon, Fugitive Information, Little Deaths with Janie Geiser, Vow: The Way of the Milagro with Richard Downing, (box of milagros included in book), and A Peculiar Alchemy: A Centennial History of SAR, 1907-2007. Copies of some published books have been removed for separate cataloging and can be found using the online catalog., 326940 (Box 5)
  - "Glass Dream" puppet performance script, Janie Geiser, 326939 (Box 8)
  - Ortiz Center, University of New Mexico, inaugural report, 326938 (Box 8)
  - Various copy writing projects, 326937 (Box 8)
  - "box" with Paul Vogt, 326936 (Box 8)
  - Linda Finnell catalog, SMU, for her posthumous exhibit, Sometimes My Hand Has a Mind of Its Own, personal essay, 326935 (Box 8)
  - "Self-Seeing" artist book with photos, Hagan's text, bound by Linda Finnell, 326934 (Box 8)
  - "The Need To Know", non-fiction in progress re: nuclear power, 326933 (Box 8)
  - Los Alamos National Lab, site-wide environmental impact statement, 9 issues of employee newsletter written and produced by Hagan, 326932 (Box 8)
  - Daimon, full set of poetry quarterly produced by Atlanta Poetry Collective, of which Hagan was a member, 326931 (Box 8)
  - "Synaps", artist book bound by Hagan, 326930 (Box 8)
  - Poetry, late 1960s-2011, 326929 (Box 11)
  - Illustrated draft versions of unpublished manuscript "Internal Affairs", an illustrated "biomythography", early 1980s, 326928 (Box 11)
  - Fugitive Information pamphlet series. Early versions of essays later published as monograph. Subscribers were invited to comment on draft forms of essays. Hagan met with subscribers at her engagements around the country., 326927 (Box 15)
  - Outline of A Peculiar Alchemy, 326926 (Box 15)
  - Index card file of writing ideas, 326925 (Box 18)
- Other Professional Activities and Personal History, 1955-2012, 326873; 8 boxes
  - Research files, 326904
    - Mary Daly, 326923 (Box 10)
    - Louise Bourgeois, 326922 (Box 10)
    - Voltairine de Cleyre, 326921 (Box 10)
    - Harriet Gill, 326920 (Box 10)
    - Mary Coon Walters, 326919 (Box 10)
    - Elizabeth Shepley Sergeant, 326918 (Box 10)
    - Diane Fowlkes interview, for research on feminisms, 1984, 326917 (Box 10)
    - Forces of Nature, 326916 (Box 10)
    - Handmaid's Tale redux, 326915 (Box 10)
    - Kathleen Carlin, 326914 (Box 10)
    - Long range planning, 326913 (Box 10)
    - Promisekeepers, 326912 (Box 10)
    - Branks, chastity belt, 326911 (Box 10)
    - Jenna Weston, women's symbol language, 326910 (Box 10)
    - Anglo blues readings, 326909 (Box 10)
    - Male violence, 326908 (Box 10)
    - Men, misc., 326907 (Box 10)
    - Feminism and men, 326906 (Box 10)
    - Feminism, misc., 326905 (Box 10)
  - Charis Books & More, 326898
    - Consulting session, July 2002, 326903 (Box 10)
    - First gift guide designed by Hagan, 326902 (Box 10)
    - Minutes, 1982, 326901 (Box 10)
    - Dinner Party annex file, 1982-1984, 326900 (Box 10)
    - Long-range planning and development, 1981, 326899 (Box 10)
  - Forrest Avenue Consortium (later Nexus Contemporary Art Center and Press), 326897 (Box 10)
  - White Women's Group, 326896 (Box 10)
  - Teaching files, 326895 (Box 12)
  - Training on diversity, anti-sexism, etc., 326894 (Box 12)
  - Public speaking, 326893 (Box 12)
  - Feminar women's study groups, 326892 (Box 13)
  - Journal keeping workshops, 326891 (Box 13)
  - Michigan Womyn's Music Festival, 1987-2000, 326890 (Box 14)
  - Radical Thought Conference for Women, Cleveland OH, 1987, 326889 (Box 14)
  - Pagoda meditation/facilitation, 326888 (Box 14)
  - Sonia Johnson mediation account, 326887 (Box 14)
  - Other gigs, 326886 (Box 14)
  - School for Advanced Research files, 1998-2012, 326885 (Box 15)
  - Tewa water project, 326884 (Box 15)
  - Personal history, including photos, degrees, high school yearbook, baby book, 1955 Bible, Tara Kelton, siblings and parents, 326883 (Box 16)
  - Obama for America and Organizing for America, 2008-2012, materials collected as volunteer organizer, 326882 (Box 17)
  - Publicity photos, 326881 (Box 17)
  - Janie Geiser postcards, 326880 (Box 17)
  - Inscribed Pearl Cleage novel, 326879 (Box 17)
  - Mary Daly's Gyn/Ecology, rebound by Linda Finnell, 326878 (Box 17)
  - Y2K notebook, prep, and training, 326877 (Box 17)
  - Who We Are, Outland-produced lesbian ethics question deck, 326876 (Box 17)
  - "Nazi Designers of Death" NOVA documentary, 326875 (Box 17)
  - "The Invisible War" (depleted uranium documentary), 326874 (Box 17)
- Recordings, 1979-1987, 326860; 1 box; All recordings are on both audiocassettes and CDs.
  Original audiocassettes are closed to use. Use of these materials requires production of use copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Readings, 326866
    - "Waiting for a Wave" with Shay Youngblood, Charis Books, 1987, 326872 (Box 17)
    - "Hello/Ciao" with Terrill Soules, Catbird Gallery, Atlanta, 1979, 326871 (Box 17)
    - "Ticket to Paris" with Shay Youngblood, Charis Books, 326870 (Box 17)
    - Websters Reading (writing group), Charis Books, 1987, 326869 (Box 17)
    - "The 5 Types of Men", Atlanta, hosted by Zaron Burnett, 1988, 326868 (Box 17)
    - Interview by Linda Finnell using the Imago questionnaire, 326867 (Box 17)
  - Radical Thought Conference, 1987, 326861
    - Power, Consciousness and Radical Acts, Sallie Tatnall, Jeanette Silvera, 326865 (Box 17)
    - Lindy Comy on women's health and cancer, 326864 (Box 17)
    - Football and Feminism, Julia Penelope, 326863 (Box 17)
    - Report to Atlanta community on the conference, Charis Books, 1987, 326862 (Box 17)
- Graphic Materials, 326853; 1 box
  - Janie Geiser drawings, 326859 (Box 19)
  - Richard Downing photographs, 326858 (Box 19)
  - Linda Finnell drawings, photographs, slides, 326857 (Box 19)
  - Earliest show posters from Forrest Avenue Consortium/3rd Floor Gallery, later Nexus Contemporary Art Center (Moving Parts, Captured Light, Magic Show), 326856 (Box 19)
  - Kay Hagan photo at Southern Women's Music Festival, 326855 (Box 19)
  - Original cover art for Internal Affairs, first edition and Harper & Row edition, 326854 (Box 19)